Hello everyone and welcome back
to English Pod, my name is Marco.
And my name is Catherine
and today we have a cold lesson.
That's right.
It's the winter season
and of course it gets
cold in a lot of
different places around
the world and so we're
going to talk about heating.
Okay, this is very
important but before we
do get started we have a very important
word to preview in the vocabulary preview.
Very cabaret-y preview.
Alright, so we're going to
preview the word freezing.
It is freezing today by
the way, so this is very
appropriate, freezing
means very, very cold.
Okay, it is freezing, okay, so
it's very cold, it's freezing today.
It's so cold in fact you can't have water
outside because the water will become ice.
It will freeze.
Okay, great word so let's listen to
our dialogue for the very first time.
It's freezing in here,
can I turn up the heat?
Don't touch that thermostat,
you don't pay the bills around here.
Dad, are you serious, what's the point of
having central heating if we can't use it?
Look, I can see my breath.
Put on a sweater, I'm not
going to let you run up
my heating bill just
because it's a bit chilly.
Dad, I'm going to catch a cold.
When I was your age, my parents
didn't have central heating like you do.
We had a furnace in the center
of the living room and that was it.
We used it to cook, heat the
house and even dry our clothes.
We never caught a cold,
you should be grateful.
Alright, we're back
and this is actually
what a lot of dads are like,
I think, around the world.
Yep, my dad definitely liked
to keep the heat low, really.
Alright, so we'll talk about
that a little bit later, but let's
take a look at some four words
on language takeaway today.
Language takeaway.
Well, this first word is
important for anyone
who has a home with
heating, it's called a thermostat.
Alright, a thermostat,
what is a thermostat?
A thermostat is a dial or
like a device on the wall
that tells you how hot
or how cold the house is.
It's like a thermometer for your house.
Ok, so you can move the
thermostat, the temperature
to make the house
warmer or colder, right?
Right, so if it says
it's 20 degrees and I
think that's too cold, I can turn
the thermostat up to 23 degrees.
Alright, and well, very much
related to a thermostat and
what this device does is our
next word, central heating.
Right, so if you have
central heating, you
have a thermostat, that's
the way to control the heat.
And central heating means that you
have one heater for the whole house.
And so the air comes
into all the different rooms.
So not many places
in China have this, but
for example, in the United States,
in Canada, it is very common.
Ok, so your house or
your apartment building
will have central
heating and then you can
control how cold or warm
the house is with thermostat.
Exactly.
Very good, and well, our next word
is related to temperature and it's chili.
Chili, ok, so there's a big
difference between chili and freezing.
Freezing means very, very, very cold.
Chili means a little cold.
Right, so it's a little
cold, it's a bit chilly.
Right, so it's a bit chilly
today, I'm going to wear a hat.
Ok, if it's freezing, I'm
going to wear a hat, a
hat and mittens and a
scarf and coat and boots.
Alright, so if it's a bit
chilly, it's not very cold.
And while moving on, the dad mentioned about
him having a furnace when he was young.
That's right, the dad
had a furnace in his house
and the furnace is a
way to heat your house.
It's like a stove.
So yeah, just consider
it like a big oven, right?
Maybe you've seen it in the old
movies where you would have to
throw firewood into the furnace
to make it heat up the house.
Exactly, and so this is
very common in older
homes and not very
common in apartments.
Right, and well, that's all the words
we have for language take away today.
Why don't we listen to
this chili dialogue again?
It's freezing in here,
can I turn up the heat?
Don't touch that thermostat,
you don't pay the bills around here.
Dad, are you serious?
What's the point of having
central heating if we can't use it?
Look, I can see my breath.
Put on a sweater, I'm not
going to let you run up
my heating bill just
because it's a bit chilly.
Dad, I'm going to catch a cold.
When I was your age, my parents
didn't have central heating like you do.
We had a furnace in the center
of the living room and that was it.
We used it to cook, heat the
house, and even dry our clothes.
We never caught a cold.
You should be grateful.
All right, we're
back, so now we have
prepared for you three key
phrases on fluency builder.
Fluency Builder.
Okay, so this first phrase is
related to thermostat, okay?
So thermostat,
like we said, is like a
thermometer, but we can
control the temperature.
So, if we want to make the temperature
hotter, we turn up thermostat.
So this is a phrasal verb
to turn up, turn up the heat.
You can say this about heat,
you can say this about noise, too.
Can you turn up the radio?
Turn up the volume, so it's to increase.
To increase, to make
bigger or warmer or louder.
All right, and if we
wanted to decrease the
temperature in the thermostat, you
would say, turn down, turn down the heat.
Exactly.
So it's too hot in here.
You please turn down the heat.
All right, very good.
And our next phrase
is, well, the dad was
talking about the bills
and how expensive it
is to use a thermostat,
and he said, I'm
not going to let you
run up my heating bill.
Okay, so a bill is like, you
know, something that you pay.
It's money.
And so in this case, I don't
want you to run up the bill.
That means to increase the
amount of money I have to spend.
So maybe if you leave
your television on all
night, you're running
up your electricity bill.
Exactly.
Or if you talk on the
phone 10 hours a day, you
run up the phone bill
and your mother kills you.
All right.
And well, the daughter was complaining
about her catching a cold, too catch a cold.
All right.
So remember this, a
cold is when you have
maybe a runny nose and
the cough and the sore
throat.
It usually happens when the weather
changes, but we don't get a cold.
To catch a cold, and
remember like in baseball,
you throw and catch,
it's something that's fast.
All right.
So you catch a cold.
What about the flu?
Do you get the flu or catch the flu?
So you can't catch a flu,
but you can't catch a cold.
Just remember this phrase, to
catch a cold, I caught the cold, no.
To catch a cold or I
caught a cold, it's almost
like, if I have it, I could
throw it to you, Marco.
All right, you catch
it, because it's in the
air, the virus, yeah,
it passes very quickly.
All right.
Very good.
So an interesting dialogue.
Let's listen to it one last time.
It's freezing in here.
Can I turn up the heat?
Don't touch that thermostat.
You don't pay the bills around here.
Dad, are you serious?
What's the point of having
central heating if we can't use it?
Look.
I can see my breath.
Put on a sweater.
I'm not going to let you run up my heating
bill just because it's a bit chilly.
Dad, I'm going to catch a cold.
When I was your age, my parents
didn't have central heating like you do.
We had a furnace in the center
of the living room, and that was it.
We used it to cook, heat the
house, and even dry our clothes.
We never caught a cold.
You should be grateful.
All right, we're back,
and you mentioned about
the thermostat and your dad actually
controlling the heating at home.
Was this the case like
this in this scenario?
It was sometimes we'd have to wear more
clothes because we didn't want to run up the
bill, but we had a
special situation in my
house because I'm
from Chicago and it's very
cold in the winters in
Chicago, but we had a fireplace.
Even if it was very cold,
we always had firewood
and we could put on
the fire in the fireplace
to keep warm so everyone
would stay in the living
room and read and listen
to music and just relax.
No, I heard that because when you're burning
wood, it causes some pollution, in some
cities it's banned to actually
turn on or to have a fireplace.
That's right.
But in Chicago, you can still do it.
Absolutely.
That's right, it creates
you can, although a
lot of people in new
houses they don't have real
fireplaces, they have
electric fireplaces and
so you can use a light
switch to turn on your fire.
It's not a real fire.
It's just a glowing light.
Yeah.
All right, well, very good.
This is an interesting lesson, especially
because the winter season is coming up and
well, everyone is cold,
so we hope you enjoyed
it and if you have any
questions, any doubts,
you can come to our
website, www.EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you there.
Happy studies and stay warm.
All right, everybody.